Once I was on Red Square and there
как-то Я был на Красной площади и там
young people from the country of Dagestan were filming
молодые люди с страны Дагестан снимали
a video about how they are from what
видеоролик о том как они с какой
country Dagestan Dagestan and from the country
страны Дагестан Дагестан а со страны
Dagestan as I understood it, that is, they
Дагестан так понял то есть они из
came from Dagestan to Russia to visit you on
Дагестана приехали в Россию к вам на
Red Square Yes, absolutely
Красную площадь Да совершенно
right Hello Hello  I’m from the
верно Здравствуйте Здравствуйте я из
city of Khmelnitsky, you’re from Kaluga, I
города Хмельницкий Вы откуда з Калуга о
know this is near Moscow, yeah, yes, I
знаю это под Москвой Угу данно У вас Я
read the news from you. Yes, in the Kaluga region,
читал новости Да что в Калужской области
more than 30% of these visitors from other
более 30% уже этих приезжих из других
countries are already there.
стран там Таджикистан устан да да в
in the
Таджикистана А почему почему именно в
Kaluga region they don’t
Калужской области не
come because the Kaluga region
приезжают потому что у Калужской области
has a conflict with Moscow. That’s why
с Москвой возник конфликт Вот и поэтому
they redirect
перенаправляет для регистрации
immigrants to us for registration and that’s why they stay
иммигрантов к нам и поэтому они остатся
for a few days for months. It happens
на на на несколько дней на месяца Бывает
even for years to
даже на года для того чтобы оформить
register. Cool yes And how the locals
регистрацию Прикольно да И как местные
treat  to this there uh let's
относятся к этому там
say so if they behaved
ээ скажем так если бы они себя бы вели
normally it would be
бы нормально бы
normal But let's say they often
то нормально Но скажем так часто
come across Gra Well let's say so
попадаются Гра Ну скажем так
negative attitude because
отрицательному отношению потому что
once I was on Red Square and there
как-то я был на Красной площади и там
young people from the country of Dagestan
молодые люди с страны Дагестан та
were filming a video about how  from which
снимали видеоролик о том как с какой
country is Dagestan Dagestan and from the country
страны Дагестан Дагестан а со страны
Dagestan so I understood that is, they
Дагестан так понял то есть они из
came from Dagestan to Russia to see you on
Дагестана приехали в Россию к вам на
Red Square Yes, absolutely right Well,
Красную площадь Да совершенно верно Ну
after all, look at the architecture of the capital
всё-таки посмотрите архитектуру столицу
and even this video ended up in the video
так вот и даже этот ролик попал в видео
sows general where I’m filming what
сеет общие где я снимаю то что
Dagestanis are clearing their land But this is
дагестанцы очищают свою землю Но это
generally ugly, well, to the max.
некрасиво вообще ну максимально
Cool, but it turns out well, look. Um,
Прикольно а получается ну смотрите Ээ
how do you feel about the fact that migrants from
как вы относитесь того что мигранты из
Dagestan come to Russia
Дагестана приезжают в Россию
honestly neutral no let’s say there are bad
честно нейтрально нету скажем так плохих
countries there are bad people Yeah I understand and
стран есть плохие люди Угу понял а
the capital of Dagestan Which one can you tell me I’m
столица Дагестана Какая не подскажете я
not strong Oh I  I won’t tell you for sure, but
не силён Ой я вам точно сам не скажу а
Makhachkala is like Makhachkala, yes, that is, am I
Махачкала вроде Махачкала да то есть ли
interested in Dagestan? But what do you
дагестаном увлекаюсь А вы вот ну как вы
think in Kaluga? Should Russia maintain a
считаете в Калуге Должна ли Россия Вести
visa regime with Dagestan so that they
визовый режим с дагестаном чтобы они не
cannot freely come to Russia, yes, but
могли свободно приезжать в Россию да а
only receive visas, for example,
получали только визы например
certain types of
определённые ти
workers, yes  I think it’s not necessary Yes, no it’s not
работников да я думаю не надо Да нет не
necessary Well, if they are good di Well, yes But
надо Ну так если они хорошие ди Ну да Но
you don’t like that everyone goes from
вам не нравится что все подряд едут из
Dagestan to Russia, yes, maybe it’s necessary,
Дагестана в Россию да может нужно как
like between countries, yes, that is, to
вот между странами да то есть чтобы
do it, for example, a person from
сделали например хочет человек из
Dagestan wants to come to Russia Yes he  shows
Дагестана приехать в Россию Да он подаёт
that he is not just some kind of Robber
что он не просто какой-то там Разбойник
Yes, but he is just a good specialist
Да а он просто хороший специалист
gets a visa and comes to Russia, you can
получает визу и приезжает в Россию можно
do this Well, what should other people do
сделать Ну а что делать другим людям
who
которы
can prove that they are Why do
могут доказать что они А зачем зачем вам
you need someone to come from Dagestan for
чтобы вас приезжали из Дагестана
example?  bandits and so
какие-то там например бандиты и так
on Yes, if he goes to work in
дальше Да вот если он едет на работу в
Russia, ordinary people. Well, what
Росси обычные люди Ну а что что обычный
will an ordinary person do in your country of
человек будет делать у вас из страны
Dagestan? He will come to the country of Russia and will
Дагестан приедет в страну Россия и будет
do something in Moscow, what will he do?
у вас делать в Москве чем он будет
Well, if about migrants he will
заниматься Ну это если про мигрантов
immediately earn money  because, after all,
сразу зарабатывать потому что всё-таки
oh, after all, because the money is different, the
ой вс-таки потому что другие деньги
salary is still different. That is, for
вс-таки другая заработная плата То есть
example, what
можно например
they do most often is some
делают они чаще всего какой-нибудь
eldest son from the family comes to another
старший сын из семьи приезжают другую
country to provide for his family, that’s
страну чтобы обеспечить свою семью вот у
how it works for them  okay,
них же так это работает вот а хорошо
nothing against And the question: Yes, for example, there is,
ничего против А вопрос Да например есть
I know that there is also a country called Tatarstan.
вот я знаю что ещё есть страна Татарстан
Yes, it has that there. Do you think
Да у неё там то есть Как вы считаете
migrants from Tatarstan have the right to
мигранты из Татарстана имеют право
come to Russia or should
приезжать в Россию или тоже должно быть
their number also be somehow limited, as with
как-то ограничено ихнее количество как с
Dagestan? No, why not?  Please
дагестаном Да нет почему же Пожалуйста
let them come Yes, I understand, it’s good if you
пусть приезжают Да поня а хорошо если
choose a priority, where do you
вот выбирать приоритет откуда вам больше
like best? Migrants from Dagestan,
нравятся вот мигранты из Дагестана
Tatarstan, Bashkortostan, for example, from the
Татарстана Башкортостана например из
Republic of Sakha. I just don’t communicate with people like that.
Республики Саха Я с такими просто не
I don’t know these people. I’ll say it as
общаюсь Я не знаю этих людей скажу как
just a former athlete, the Dagestanis are
просто бывший спортсмен дагестанцы они
very good at promoting the development of sports,
очень хорошо поднимают развитию спорта
that is  Dagestanis are such a fighting
то есть дагестанцы они такой боевой же
people, they are quite good at
народ довольно-таки и очень хорошо
participating in MMA in different countries, which is
участвует в MMA в разных странах на что
very well
очень хорошо
influenced by different countries, after all, they are
влияет разных стран всё-таки они Они же
in different countries and compete for different
в разных странах и выступают за разные
countries. That’s why
страны Вот и поэтому ничего против не
I have nothing against it because they are fighting  they are people Well,
имею потому что они боевой народ они Ну
I have a lot of pretty familiar
у меня много довольно-таки знакомых
Dagestanis who were athletes.
дагестанцев которые спортсмены были Вот
But
Но
alas, they gave up theirs, they gave up their hobby of
увы бросили свою бросили своё хобби
sports and went to work for the benefit of
спорт и ушли работать ради во благо
their family in order to provide for it, I
своей семьи для того чтобы её обеспечить
understand. Well, look, what do you
понял А хорошо а вот смотрите Как вы
think? For example, if a migrant is from
считаете Например если мигрант из
Dagestan  Yes, it violates some kind of
Дагестана Да нарушает какое-то там
legislation of the Russian Federation,
законодательство Российской Федерации
for example, there are traffic rules,
например там правила дорожного движения
or there is something on Red Square that does
или там вот как-то на Красной площади
not behave as you think. Should
ведёт не так как вы считаете Должны ли
violating migrants from
депортировать нарушающих мигрантов из
Dagestan be deported back to the country of Dagestan from
Дагестана назад в страну Дагестан из
Russia, let’s say, as a lawyer, depending on the
России смотря скажем как юрист смотря на
degree of violation  For example, if this is a
степень нарушения Например если это
criminal case, then in
уголовно наказуемое дело то здесь уже в
any case, migration is in any
любом случае миграция это в любом
case an administrative offense. And what level are
случае административное правонарушение А
you, a lawyer, third,
вы на каком ку юрист на третьем на
third? Well, it’s quite easy to
третьем Ну довольно просто хорошо
argue well. I just thought you were some kind of IT
рассуждать Я просто думал вы какие-то ну
specialist. What if you’re a lawyer? Yes,
просто там айтишники А если юрист Да
very  think correctly Yes, if it’s
очень правильно мыслить Да если
administrative Well, that’s Yes, if it’s already a
административка Ну такое Да если уже
crime, yes Well, that’s already a fine, that’s already a
криминал да Ну это уже штраф это уже
fine, and you need to deport
штраф таки и нужно депортировать типа
him like then to Dagestan Well, to his homeland and
тогда его в Дагестан Ну на его родину и
his country, why not just, well, as
его страну не почему же просто ну как
they say, you know, ignorance of the laws does not
говорится знаете ли незнание законов не
exempt you from responsibility  so yes, it’s
освобождает от ответственности вот так
very correctly said Yes, but it’s
что да очень правильно сказано Да а вот
good
хорошо
another question What do you
ещ такой вопрос Как вы
think? So you, as a lawyer, look at
считаете Вот вы как юрист смотрите
crime among migrants from
преступность среди мигрантов из
Dagestan, it is at the same level as in the
Дагестана она на таком же уровне как У
local population of the Russian Federation,
местного населения Российской Федерации
or higher or
или выше или
lower, according to statistics, I’ll say, for example, in the
ниже по статистике скажу например в
country of Dagestan it’s quite  - there is an
стране Дагестана довольно-таки
increased degree of crime because,
повышенная степень преступности потому
after all, it has still moved away from the early 1900s,
что всё-таки ещё отошло от дех годов
because people came from different countries after all, the
потому что из разных стран приезжали
collapse of the Soviet Union and a
развал Советского союза и
completely free country and
полностью свободная страна и полностью
everyone completely started doing what Dana wanted, for
все все начали делать Что хотели Дане
example,
например
even in Dagestan, even in the new Russia,
даже в Дагестане даже и в новой России
then  there is everything, everything has come together and
то есть вс всё склалось между собой и
therefore the crime rate
поэтому преступность даже процент
practically does not fall, both among the Russians and
практически не падает что у русских что
among the Dagestanis, but still, as I say, there are
у дагестанцев но всё-таки как я и говорю
no bad nations, there are bad people,
нету плохих Наций есть плохие люди
so the level is higher in your opinion. Where is the
поэтому тако выше уровень по-вашему Где
crime level higher in the past in Dagestan,
выше уровень преступности ране дагеста
I think  the fact that in the country of the Russian
Я считаю то что в стране Российской
Federation, after all, we are a large-scale
Федерации всё-таки мы крупномасштабная
country and still quite a lot of
страна и всё-таки довольно-таки много
history is connected with us, so you
история с нами связана поэтому от них
can’t wash them away, after all, there were a lot of
уже не отмоешь всё-таки много было
violations and this can be denied Glu
нарушений и этого этого отрицать Глу
look, but if the country of Dagestan,
смотрите а е если страна Дагестана
for example, this is how it is  Ukraine wanted
например вот как Украина вот захотела
to join NATO. So you know this
вступить в НАТО Так вы знаете эту
story. Yes, if the country of Dagestan also, the
историю Да если страна Дагестан тоже вот
parliament of Dagestan will vote on
парламент Дагестана проголосует о том
joining NATO. What do you think?
чтобы войти в НАТО Как вы считаете
Should Russia send troops to
Должна ли Россия ввести войска в
Dagestan to prevent the
Дагестан чтобы не допустить вхождения
country of Dagestan from joining NATO in the NATO bloc? No no
страны Дагестан в НАТО в блок НАТО Нет
not  should introduce should not And why was they
нет не должна вводить не должна А почему
introduced into Ukraine
в Украину ввели
when I just know the information that a
тогда как просто знаю информацию то что
memorandum was signed stating that
был подписан меморандум о том то что
Ukraine is not joining NATO Well, it
Украина не вступает в НАТО Ну так а
turns out well, that is, Russia did not want
получается ну то есть Россия не хотела
Ukraine to join NATO and attacked
чтобы Украина вступала в НАТО и напала
Ukraine because  this
на Украину из-за этого
yes mm most likely in order to
да мм скорее всего для того чтобы
eliminate the problem and in order to, let’s
ликвидировать - проблему и для того
say, not resolve the conflict
чтобы скажем так не решать конфликт
because after all, problems with Ukraine have
потому что всё-таки с Украиной уже
slowly begun to arise with
потихоньку начали быть проблемы с
Russia, yeah Well, okay, but
Россией вот уга Ну хорошо а вот если
if it’s real Yes, Dagestan will see what’s
если реально Да Дагестан посмотрит что
wrong with it  the NATO bloc will be somehow
ээ ему с блоком НАТО будет как-то
more interesting and will sign Well, he will want to
интереснее и подпишет Ну захочет
join the NATO bloc so that
вступить в блок НАТО чтобы натовские
there are NATO bases in the country of Dagestan How should
базы были в стране Дагестан Как должна
Russia attack sovereign Dagestan
ли Россия напасть на суверенный Дагестан
in this
в таком
case No should not should not understand that is,
случае Нет не должна не должна понял то
Russia should respect
есть Россия должна уважать решение
Dagestan’s decision to join NATO  I
Дагестана о вступлении в НАТО я
understand absolutely correctly, she
правильно понимаю абсолютно она она
must respect every opinion, but as I
должна уважать каждое мнение но как я
know from general sources,
знаю из источников общих Вот был
a memorandum was signed on what Ukraine and
подписан меморандум на что Украина с
Dagestan have. Maybe some kind of
дагестаном есть Может какой-то
memorandum with Dagestan and Tatarstan. Not
меморандум с дагестаном с татарстаном Не
joining NATO. Oh, I can’t tell you for sure, I
вступлении в НАТО Ой точно вам не скажу
haven’t seen the documents in  eyes Uh-huh, I understand. Well, what do
ю документы не видел в глаза Угу понял А
you think? For example,
хорошо а как вы считаете Вот например
as a lawyer, uh, the
как юрист
legislation of Dagestan Yes, it is
ээ законодательство Дагестана Да оно
more backward than the legislation of the
более отсталой чем законодательство
Russian Federation or not. Or have you not
Российской Федерации или нет Или вы не
compared it with the legislation of these two
сравнивали с законодательство этих двух
countries? No no, why is it far from the
стран нет нет почему же далеко не так
same fines, except that they have
такие же штрафы только разве что у них
criminal liability is much
уголовная ответственность намного
increased in the sense of much increased angles of
повышено смысле намного повышено углов
responsibility, that is, the catch is
ответственность то есть улав
responsible for them. For example, if in our country they
ответственно у них Например если у нас
give 3-4 years for murder, then they can get up
за убийство дают 3-4 года то у них могут
to 8 years there in Russia for murder 3-4
там вй до 8 лет в России за убийство 3-4
years Well, approximately depending on the degree of
года Ну примерно смотря на степень
violation not  It seems to me that Well, I just
нарушения не Мне кажется Ну я просто
know about murder in Ukraine, but obviously not 3-4
знаю убийство в Украине но явно не 3-4
years, but if it’s intentional, like
года да если это умышленно типа
Well, it seems to me that in Russia you can’t
Ну мне кажется что в России не может
get 34 years for murder. You’re definitely a lawyer,
быть за убийство 34 года Вы точно юрист
depending on the degree of violation, if it’s
смотря на степень нарушения если
intentional, then it can get there But that’s
умышленно то там может дойти Но это
in general  as the prosecutor's office will decide, let's
вообще как уже решит
look at the Criminal Code of the Russian
вот смотрим Уголовный Кодекс Российской
Federation, article 105 murder murder
Федерации статья 105 убийство убийство
does not seem to be imprisonment For a term of 6
на кажется лишением свободы На срок от 6
to 15 years 3-4 cannot
до 15 лет 3-4 не может
be Well most likely I meant it
быть Ну скорее всего это я имел в виду
unintentionally I did not read further details
неумышленно я не читал дальше детали
Yes there Just looking at  degree of
Да там Просто смотря на степень
violation That is, if there is consumption of
нарушения То есть если там употребление
food there with particular severity, that is,
в еду там с особой тяжестью то есть
consumption of what you
употребление что вы имели в
meant, well, of course, we have such a thing. Of course,
виду ну у нас конечно у нас такого
there is no exact name, but
Конечно нет названия прям вот точного Но
I’ll say it directly as a person, cannibalism, and that
скажу прямо как человек каннибализм а то
is, if someone was killed and
есть если ког убили и
imprisoned, for example, Yes  for example, prisoners
сажали например Да например заключённые
in prison go
в тюрме йде
Dolphin, I don’t know such a story, there are
Дельфин не знаю такой истории вот там
such citizens who used
вот такие граждане которые употребляли
people for food, it’s
людей в еду
cool and how much they
прикольно и на сколько их
were sentenced,
осудили
no, why did one Cannibal
вот нет почему же один э Каннибал
serve 20 years, once he was already imprisoned in 990,
отсидел 20 лет раз э уже то и сел в 990
what year and then got out  in the twenty-
каком там году и вот вышел в двадцать
first year,
первом году
but he is isolated from society completely
но он изолирован от общества полностью
as isolated as who isolated him where he
как изолирован кто его изолировал где он
lives he was isolated by the Ministry of
живёт его изолировал Министерство
Internal Affairs in his own
внутренних дел в его же квартире
registration apartment That is, he is allowed
прописки То есть ему разрешается
to go outside there for 15-20
выходить на улицу там в течение 15-20
minutes under That is, he still goes out  yes,
минут под То есть он всё-таки выходит да
absolutely right, for 15-20 minutes there to
совершенно верно на 15-20 минут там
breathe some air, you look, you went to
подышать воздухо вы смотрите вы вы пошли
become a lawyer, you want to then be a lawyer, a
на юриста вы хотите потом быть адвокатом
prosecutor, an investigator, who does he want to
прокурором следователем кем он хочет
be a
быть
rock musician,
рок-музыкантов
he wants to be a rock musician, if
он хочет быть рок музыкантом если
seriously, I considered it, I
серьёзно то рассматривал
didn’t consider it, the department for the prosecutor’s office didn’t consider it, I did
я отдел по прокуратура не рассматривал
n’t consider it  you
рассматривал не рассматривал ты это
just don’t know it, didn’t consider it And the
просто не знаешь не рассматривал А
girl and who are you? Teach it so you
девушка а вы на кого Учите ещё так за
know everything for him businessman designer
него всё знаете деловод дизайнер
designer designer family designer and
дизайнер дизайнер семейный дизайнер а
designer That’s exactly what I understood You’re a very
дизайнер Это точно понял У вас очень
smart, educated man I
умный образованный мужчина мне
liked this conversation usually you know
понравилось этот разговор обычно знаете
some kind of drunken redneck there uneducated
какое-то пьяное [__] там необразованная
here we seriously talked about both geography and
тут серьёзно мы и по географии и по
conduct, my
проведению поговорили очень у меня
man is very good, that’s why I
мужчина очень хороший поэтому я на нём и
actually married him. Yes, you got married, got
женилась реально Да ти ой вышла замуж
married, Lord, I understand. I’m an
женилась Господи Поня Это я
uneducated, drunken redneck, and he
необразованная пьяная быдла а он хороший
understands well.
понял Да согласен да хорошо у вас ко мне
then there is a question
какой-то вопрос
No There is no That everything will go well
есть Нет Не имеется Что хорошо всё пойду
means look, I still
значит смотрите я всё-таки как
kind of want to point out that you have very sensible
бы хочу отметить что у вас очень здравые
thoughts that Russia should not, for example,
мысли что Россия не должна например
attack Dagestan if Dagestan
нападать на Дагестан если Дагестан
wants to join NATO because it is necessary to
захочет войти в НАТО потому что нужно
respect the sovereign sovereignty of Dagestan
уважать суверен суверенитет Дагестана
his
его
opinion of this  states
мнение этого государства
yes of all countries yes good Everything Let's
даста всех стран да хорошо Всё Давайте
all All the best You are a very good
всё Всего доброго Вы очень хороший
person goodbye Okay let's
человек до свидания Хорошо
[ __ ] Yak you can be a lawyer in your third
бля Як можно быт юристом на третьем
year and perceive that Dagestan
курсе и воспринимать что Дагестан у тебя
is a separate country for you yes Oh well,
это отдельная страна
good trends are good Yes,
да О ну хорошие тенденции хорошие
give me a plus sign who liked
Да мне поставте плюсик кому понравилось
these  conversation write on th Telegram
эти этот разговор пись на й Telegram
right now he is
прям зараз он а
more and more
пок це дуже и дуже
polite
важливо